<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A reporte of maister doctor Redmans answeres, to questions propounded him before his death concernynge certaine poyntes of religion, now beyng with many in controuersye. Whervnto diuerse artycles be added, lately subscribed by Master Chedsey.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1551</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10555</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20827</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106074</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841799</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841799</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6406</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10555)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6406)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1332:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A reporte of maister doctor Redmans answeres, to questions propounded him before his death concernynge certaine poyntes of religion, now beyng with many in controuersye. Whervnto diuerse artycles be added, lately subscribed by Master Chedsey.</title>
                  <author>Chedsey, Master.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Raynalde in Paules churche yeard for Wylliam Seres, dwellyng at the west syde of Paules towarde Ludgate, at the signe of the hedge hog],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1551.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's and publisher's names from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A B⁴(-B4).</note>
                  <note>Considerable print show-through; some leaves cropped at head.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Redman, John, 1499-1551.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6406:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6406:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ A reporte of Maiſter Doctor Redmans anſweres, to queſtions propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him before his death, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernynge certaine poyntes of religion, now beyng with many in contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſye. Whervnto diuerſe artycles be added, late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubſcribed by Maſter Chedſey.</p>
            <p>☞ Trye all thynges, and take that whiche is good.</p>
            <p>1551.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6406:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6406:2"/>
            <head>¶ The Printer to the Reader.</head>
            <p>BEcauſe I had harde ſundrye and dyſagreynge reportes of Mayſter Doctor Redmans iudgemente, in certaine pointes of religion at the tyme of his death, &amp; perceyued one daye in Maſter Secreatary Cecilles Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber at the Courte, a paper briefly contey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng the ſayinges of Maſter Redman, with the handes of dyuers learned men, ſubſcribed to teſtifye the truth therof. I beſought him to haue the coppye for the ſatiſfaction of many men, and to ſhewe me the truth of the teſtimony writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the paper it ſelfe he lent me wyllyngly, why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che (as he told me) he had in the counſel, of the Duke of Northumberla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Kynges Maieſtye delyuered it. And for the profe of the matter written, they whoſe names be ſubſcribed had affirmed the ſame partly to him ſelfe, partly to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers beſyde the teſtimony of their own handes, thus hauinge the thynge in my handes &amp; perceyuing dayly talke to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe here vpon, I thought it conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to imprint it for the ſatyſfactyon of the more nomber. And making Maſter Cecil
<pb facs="tcp:6406:3"/> pryuye of myne intent with the reaſons that moued me, he gaue to me two other wrytinges, the one written by Mayſter Doctor Wilkes &amp; belongyng to Maſter Redmans matter, thother of certaine ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tycles ſubſcribed by Maſter D. Chedſey of Oxford, a man of moch learning, and as it ſemeth yeldyng his affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng, which thing I thought not amiſſe to knytte togeather in one printe, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng the iudgement of the whole to bee meaſured by charyte, which as Saynte Paule ſayeth: thynketh not euyll, ioyeth not on wyckedneſſe, but ioyeth on truth and ſuffereth al thyngs. &amp;c. In the ſtock wherof, god graunte al the profeſſors of thy word, to plante, and grifte, the grow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng of theyr knowledge, that it maye in the ſpreadyng of the bowes brynge forth good fruyte in, worckes lyke the ſtocke.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>At Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <date>the .xii. day of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember. M.D.L.I.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6406:3"/>
            <head>¶ A Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication betwene Doctour Redman, lyinge in hys death bed, and Maiſter Nowell, ſcholemay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in Weſtminſter, and certayne other, touching certayne poyntes of chriſtes religion.</head>
            <p>IN Primis the ſayd Doctour Redman ſent for M. Nowel of hys owne minde, &amp; ſaid, he was willing to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon with hym of ſoche matters as he had moued the ſayd D. Redman of a daye or two before. And he beyng deſyred of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid M. Nowel to declare his mynde concernyng certaine poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of oure relygyon, fyrſte ſayde, aſke me what ye wyll, and I wyll anſwere you before god trulye as I thinke without any affection to the world or any worldly perſon.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6406:4"/>
            <p>Wytneſſes, Alex. Nowel, Rych. Burton, Ellis Lomas. Iohn Wryght.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſayd D. Redman ſaid that the ſea of Rome in theſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dayes is <hi>ſentina malorum,</hi> that is, a ſinke of all euyl.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Wytneſſes.</head>
               <p>Iohn yonge. Alexander Nowell: Rychard Burton, Ry. Elithorne, Edward Cratford, Ellis Lomas Iohn Wright.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Item that purgatory as the ſchole men caught it &amp; vſed it, was vngodly, &amp; that there was no ſoch kynd of purgatory, as they phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſyed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Wytneſſes.</head>
               <p>Iohn yong, Rychard Elithorn, Iohn Wryght. Alex. Nowel, Ed. Cratford, Rychard Burton, Ellis Lomas.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Item that the offering vp of the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in Maſſes &amp; Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talles
<pb facs="tcp:6406:4"/> for the ſynnes of the dead is vngodly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>☞ Wytneſſes.</head>
               <p>Iohn yong, A. Nowel, E. Crat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forde, Rycharde Burton, Ellis Lomas.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Item that the wicked ar not partakers of the body of Chriſte, but receaue the vtwarde ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t onely.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>☞ Wytneſſes.</head>
               <p>Iohn yong. Alexander Nowel Rychard Elithorn, Edward Crat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forde, Ellis Lomas, Rycharde, Burton, Iohn Wright.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Item that the Sacramente oughte not to be caryed aboute in proceſſion, for it is taught what is the vſe of it in theſe wordes, <hi>Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite manducate &amp; bibite, &amp; hoc faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te in mei memoriam.</hi> Take, eate, and drincke, and doo this in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of me.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6406:5"/>
               <p>Iohn yong, Alex. Nowel, Rych. Burton, Ioh. Wryght. El. Crat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde, Ellis Lomas.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Item that nothing whych is ſene in the ſacrament, or perceiued wyth any outwarde ſtuffe is to be worſhypped.</p>
               <p>Iohn yong, Alex. Nowel, E. Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, Ry. Burton.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that we receaue not chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes body <hi>corporaliter, id eſt craſſe,</hi> corporally, that is to ſay groſſely, lyke other meates, and lyke as the Caphernites dyd vnderſtand it.</p>
               <p>Iohn yong, A. Nowel, R. Burto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> El. Cratford, Ellis Lomas. Iohn Wright.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Item that we receaue chriſtes body <hi>ſic ſpiritualiter vt tamen vere,</hi> ſo ſpirituallye, that neuertheleſſe truely.</p>
               <p>Iohn yong, A. Nowel, R. Burto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> El. Cratford, Ellis Lomas. Iohn Wright.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb facs="tcp:6406:5"/>10. Item as touching tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiacion, that ther is not in any of the olde Doctoures anye good ground or ſure profe thereof, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mention of it, as far as euer he could perceiue, nether that he ſeith what can be aunſwered to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections made agaynſt it.</p>
               <p>Iohn yonge. Ry. Burton. Ellis Lomas.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beyng aſked of Maſter Wilkes, what that was, that was lyfted vp betwene the prieſtes han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des. he anſwered: he thought that Chriſt could nether be lyfte vp nor downe.</p>
               <p>Iohn yong, Ry. Burton. E. Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that Prieſtes may by the lawe of God marrie wyuez.</p>
               <p>Alexander Nowell. Ellis Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas.</p>
               <p n="13">13. That thys propoſition <hi>Sola fides iuſtificat,</hi> ſo that <hi>fides</hi> ſignifye
<pb facs="tcp:6406:6"/> 
                  <hi>veram viua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; acquieſcente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto fidem id eſt amplexum Chriſti.</hi> that is to ſaye: Onely fayth doeth iuſtifye, ſo that fayth do ſignifye a true lyuely, and a fayth reſtinge in chriſte, and embraſing Chriſt, is a true godly ſwete &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne ſo that it be ſo taughte, that the people take none occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nal lybertie thereof.</p>
               <p>Iohn yong, A. Nowel, R. Burto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iohn Wright. Ed. Cratford, Ry. Elithorn, Ellis Lomas.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Item that our workes can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not deſerue the kingdom of god and lyf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> euerlaſtinge.</p>
               <p>Iohn yong, Alexander Nowell, Rychard Burton, Ellis Lomas, Edward Cratford, Rychard Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorn, Iohn Wright.</p>
               <p>Item that the ſaid Doctour Red<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man at ſoche tymes as we the fore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſayde perſonnes whych haue ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrybed
<pb facs="tcp:6406:6"/> heard his communication, concerning the foreſayd pointes of religion, was of quyet mynde and of perfyte remembraunce, as farre as we were able to iudge.</p>
               <p>Iohn yong. Alexander Nowel. Rychard Burton. Ellis Lomas. Edwarde Cratford, Rychard Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorn, Iohn Wright.</p>
               <p>☞ Alſo Mayſter yonge of hym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelf doth declare further, touching the former Articles on this wyſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the .v. Article.</head>
               <p>IN Primis that Doctor Redma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayd more, where as S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine ſayd: <hi>Quod Iudas idem ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ꝙ Petrus,</hi> that Iudas receiued the ſame that Peter dyd, he ſayde: that he vnderſtode that of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramente, and that after thee ſame phraſe a manne myghte ſaye: <hi>Quod Simon magus idem Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma recepit quod Apoſtoli,</hi> That Symon Magus receaued the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me
<pb facs="tcp:6406:7"/> baptiſme that the Apoſtles dyd, when he dyd receaue only the outward ſacrament to his conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for he ſayd that he thought: chriſt wold not vouchſafe to geue his holy fleſhe to an vngodly man, and thys he ſayd was alwayes his minde, though he knew that other men dyd otherwyſe thinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the .vi. Article.</head>
               <p>Item he ſayd: he neuer lyked the cariage about of the ſacrament, &amp; preached agaynſte it, aboute a .xvi. yeares ſince in Cambridge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the .x. Article.</head>
               <p>Item when he was demaunded of tranſubſtantiacion, he ſaid: that he had trauayled about it, &amp; thinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge that the doubtes whych he perceyued dyd ryſe thereon, ſhuld be made playne by the ſchole men, dyd reade theyr bokes, and that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he had read them that the opinion of tranſubſtantiacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was
<pb facs="tcp:6406:7"/> euery daye <hi>magis &amp; magis languida</hi> that is, weaker and weaker, &amp; that there was no ſoch tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion as they made, addinge therto that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole ſchole dyd not know what was meant by conſecration, which he ſayd was the whole ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the holy Communion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>☞ To the .xiii. Article.</head>
               <p>Item he ſayd that he dyd repent him that he had ſo moch ſtriued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt iuſtification by only fayth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>☞ To the .xiiii. Article.</head>
               <p>Item that worckes hadde theyr crowne and reward, but that they dyd not deſerue eternall lyfe &amp; the Kingdom of God, no not the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of grace, <hi>Nam domini dei vita eterna.</hi> For euerlaſtinge lyfe is the gyfte of God.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6406:8"/>
            <head>¶ A Note of the Communication that I Rychard Wilkes had with M. D. Redman, beyng ſycke at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynſter, but of good memorie the ſeconde daye of Noue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber. 1551. in the preſence of Maſter Yong, &amp; an other whom I dyd not know, and two of M. D. Redmans ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, the one called Elliſe and the other vnknowen.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Wyſhed him health in ſoule and bodye, and doubted not but more he did practiſe the god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly counſayl in him ſelf, the whych he was wonte to geue to other, beyng in his caſe, &amp; thanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes be to god, who had geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym ſtuffe of knowledge to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte him ſelfe withal. Sayth he, God of all
<pb facs="tcp:6406:8"/> comfort geue me grace to haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte in him, and to haue my mynd wholye fyxed in hym. Mayſter yonge and I ſayde Amen. Then I communed wyth hym of his ſic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneſſe, and the weakeneſſe of hys bodye, &amp; though he were brought neuer ſo low, yet he, yf it were his pleaſure that rayſed vp Lazarus, coulde reſtore hym too healthe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, No no, ſayeth he: that is paſte, and I deſyre it not, but thee wyll of God be fulfylled. After thys a lyttle other lyke communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catyon, I aſked yf I myghte be ſo bolde not troublynge hym, too knowe hys mynde for my lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge in ſome matters and poync<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of Relygyon, he ſayde: yea, and that he was as glad to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wyth me in ſoche matters as wyth anye manne, and then I ſayde to hys ſeruaunces: I truſte I ſhall not trouble him, no ſayde
<pb facs="tcp:6406:9"/> Ellys his ſeruaunte, my Lorde of London M. Nowell, and other haue comuned wyth him, and he was glad of it. Then ſayd Maſter Redman no you ſhall not trouble me, I pray god euer geue me grace to ſpeake the trueth, &amp; hys trueth, and that which ſhall redounde to hys glory, and ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vs vnitie in hys church, and we ſayd. Amen. I ſaid he ſhuld do moch good in declarin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge hys fayth, and I wold be glad to knowe his mynde, as touching thee Sacramente of thee bodye and bloude of Chriſt, he ſayde as man is made of two partes, of the body, and the ſoule, ſo chriſt wold fede thee whole man, but what ſaith he be the wordes of the text, let vs take the wordes of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, and he rehearſed the text him ſelf thus, <hi>Accepit Ieſus panem,</hi> chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte toke breade, wherein hys wyll was to inſtytute a Sacramente,
<pb facs="tcp:6406:9"/> 
               <hi>Accipite commedite,</hi> take, eat, here he tolde thee vſe of it, what didde he geue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? <hi>Hoc eſt corpus meum,</hi> He calleth it his body. Then I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him of the preſence of Chriſte, he ſayd: Chriſt was preſente wyth his ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and in thoſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued it as they ought. And ther was <hi>mira vnitio,</hi> a wonderful vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (for that word was named) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Chriſt &amp; vs, as ſ. Paule ſaith <hi>Vos eſtis, os ex oſſibus eius, et caro ex carne eius,</hi> ye be bone of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; fleſhe of hys fleſhe, the why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che vnion was ineffable. Then I aſked him what he thought of the opinion that Chriſte was ther cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally, naturally, &amp; really, he aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered yf you meane by corporal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, naturally, &amp; really, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is ther preſent, <hi>Vere,</hi> I graunt. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him howe he thoughte of that which was wont commenly to be ſpoken, that chriſt was ther fleſhe
<pb facs="tcp:6406:10"/> bloud, and bone, as I haue heard the ſtewardes in theyr leetes geue charge, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſixe Articles ſtode in effecte, and dyd geue charge too thinqueſt to enquyre, that yf there were anye that woulde denye that Chriſt was preſent in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the aulter, in fleſhe, bloud, and bone, they ſhuld preſent them. He ſayd: that was to to groſſe, and could not wel be excuſed from the opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Caphernites. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I aſked him in aſmoch, as chriſt was there, <hi>Vere,</hi> howe doo we receaue hym in oure myndes and ſpirituall partes, or wyth oure mouthes and into our bodies, or bothe? he ſaid: we receaue him in our mindes and ſoules by fayth. Then in aſmoche as he was moch in this point, that there was <hi>Mira vnitio,</hi> a meruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous vnion, betwixt vs and Chriſt, in that we were <hi>Caro ex carne eius, et os ex oſſibus,</hi> bone of his bones
<pb facs="tcp:6406:11"/> and fleſhe of hys fleſhe, I deſyred to knowe his opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whether we receaued the very body of Chriſte wyth our mouthes, &amp; into our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, or no. Here he pauſed and dyd holde his peace a lytle ſpace, &amp; ſhortely after he ſpake, ſayinge: I wyl not ſaye ſo, I can not tel, it is a harde queſtion, but ſurely ſayth he: we receaue Chriſt in our ſoule by fayth, when you ſpeake of it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wayes, it ſoundeth groſſely, &amp; ſauoureth of thee Caphernites. Then I aſked him what he thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght of that whych the Prieſt was wont to lyft vp and ſhow the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple betwixt his handes, he ſayd: it is the ſacrament, then ſayd I they were wont to worſhyp that which was lifted vp, yea ſaith he: but we muſt worſhip chriſt in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Chriſt is nether lifted vp nor down, I am glad ſayde I Maſter D. to heare you ſaye ſo moche, I woulde not
<pb facs="tcp:6406:12"/> ſpeake of the holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe then reuerentlye, but I feare leſt that ſacrament and lytle white pece of breade ſo lyfted vp, hathe robbed Chryſte of a greate parte of his honour. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayd he loking vp and prayinge, god graunte vs grace that we maye haue the true vnderſtandyng of his word, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by we may come to the true vſe of his Sacramentes, &amp; ſayd he wold neuer allowe the carying about of the ſacrament &amp; other fond abuſes aboute the ſame. Then after a litle whyle pawſyng ſayd I, Mayſter Doctoure yf I ſhulde not trouble you, I wolde praye you to knowe your mynde in tranſubſtantiacion, Ieſu Mayſter Wilkes ſayeth he wyll you aſke me that? Syr ſayde I, not yf I ſhulde trouble you, no no, I wyl tel you ſayth he, becauſe I founde thopinion of tranſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation receiued in the church, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:6406:10"/> I hard it ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt, I ſerched the auncient Doctors diligently, &amp; went about to ſtabliſhe it by them, becauſe it was receaued, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I redde manye of theym, I founde lyttle for it, and could not be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed, then I went to the ſcole doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, and namely to Gabriel, and wayed hys reaſons, the whyche when I had done, and perceaued they were no pithier, <hi>Langueſcebat opinio mea, de tranſubſtantiatione,</hi> my opinion of tranſubſtantiacion waxed feble, and then ſayth he: I retourned agayne to Tertullian &amp; Ireneus, and when I hadde ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued theyr ſayinges, myne opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that there ſhuld be tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiacion, <hi>Prorſus erat abolita,</hi> was quyte daſſhed. Then ſayde I, you knowe that the ſcole Doctors dyd holde that <hi>Panis no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> remanebat poſt conſecrationem,</hi> that bread remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not after conſecration, as they
<pb facs="tcp:6406:11"/> called it. The ſcole Doctors ſayth he: dyd not know what <hi>conſecratio</hi> doeth meane, and here he pauſed a whyle, I praye you ſayd I, what ſaye you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>conſecratio</hi> doth meane, ſayth he: it is <hi>Tota actio</hi> in miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as Chriſt dyd inſtitute it. All the whole thinge done in the miniſterie as Chriſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned it, that is <hi>conſecratio,</hi> and what, ſayth he: nede we to doubte that bread remayneth. Scripture calleth it bread and certayne good Auctours that be of latter tyme, be of that opinion.</p>
            <p>After that I hadde communed with Mayſter D. Redman, &amp; take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my leaue of hym, Mayſter Yonge came forth into the nexte chambre with me, to whom I ſayde: that I was glad to ſe Maſter D. Redma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo wel mynded, then ſayth Maſter Yonge to me, I am ſure he wyll not deny it, I enſure you ſayth he:
<pb facs="tcp:6406:12"/> Maſter D. hath ſo moued me that wher as I was of that opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in certayne thinges, that I woulde haue burned and loſt my lyfe for them, now ſayth Mayſter yonge, I doubt of them, but I ſee ſayth he: a man ſhall knowe more and more by proces of tyme, and readinge and hearinge of others, and Maiſter D. Redmans ſaying ſhall cauſe me too loke more dyly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently for them.</p>
            <p>Item that Ellis Mayſter Doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tour Redmans ſeruaunte ſhewed me, that he dydde knowe that hys Mayſter had declared too Kynge Henrye the .viii. his Maieſtie, that faith onely iuſtifieth, but that doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne as he thought was not to be taught the people, leaſt they ſhuld be negligent to do good workes.</p>
            <p>The ſayd M. yonge hath repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the whych alſo I hearde that Mayſter Doctour Redman ſhuld
<pb facs="tcp:6406:13"/> ſaye, that <hi>conſenſus Eccleſie</hi> the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Church was but a wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke ſtaffe to cleaue to, but dyd ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horte hym to reade the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, for ther was that which ſhuld comfort him, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhulde be in ſoche caſe as he was then.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>❀ Imprinted at London by Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Raynalde in Paules churche yeald for Wylliam Seres, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng at the weſt ſyde of Paules towarde Ludgate, at the ſigne of the hedgehog.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>¶ Cum Priuilegio ad Imprimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Solum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6406:13"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
